<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Functions on Leonardo Zamariola</title>
    <link>https://zamariola.com.br/tags/functions/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Functions on Leonardo Zamariola</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 18:09:27 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://zamariola.com.br/tags/functions/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What is the SOLID pattern and why you should avoid it</title>
      <link>https://zamariola.com.br/post/what-is-solid-why-you-should-avoid-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 18:09:27 -0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zamariola.com.br/post/what-is-solid-why-you-should-avoid-it/</guid>
      <description>What is SOLID The SOLID is an acronym created in 2004 based on principles that Uncle Bob introduced in the 2000s to identify the best practices of software design.&#xA;💡 Disclaimer: I&amp;rsquo;m not giving a full description of the SOLID pattern because a lot of folks have done that. Digital Ocean has done that and the Uncle Bob himself has done that Although the SOLID principles may apply to any object-oriented design, they usually bring with them the Clean Code and Clean Architecture philosophies.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why and how you should code to interfaces - and high-order functions</title>
      <link>https://zamariola.com.br/post/why-and-how-you-should-code-to-interfaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2019 18:16:13 -0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zamariola.com.br/post/why-and-how-you-should-code-to-interfaces/</guid>
      <description>One famous debate that emerges in every design discussion is about interfaces. As always, each programmer has a different conception about it and it’s something almost inevitable to spend hours arguing about. Even when the discussion isn’t about whether or not we should use it, it’s about how to use it. As a programmer, I have my own opinion as well. I expect to give you an overview about the importance of interfaces when you should or not use it, and what you can apply it to.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
